{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This ruler won battles at the Hellespont and Chrysopolis to put down a revolt led by Licinius. At one battle, this man claimed he saw a Chi-Rho in the sky with the words “in this sign, you will conquer.” Maxentius was defeated by this man at the Battle of Milvian Bridge. The Edict of Milan, which granted tolerance to Christians, was issued by this emperor. For ten points, name this “Great” Roman Emperor, the first to convert to Christianity.",
      "answer": [
        "Constantine the Great",
        "Constantine I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This island’s Deltaterrasserne [“delta”-”terra”-sern] site was inhabited by the Independence I and II cultures. Archaeologists discovered the ruins of the Saqqaq culture around this island’s Disko Bay. The northernmost point of this island is named after philanthropist Morris Jesup. The US Air Force maintains Thule Base on this island, where over 30% of the population lives in the capital, Nuuk. For ten points, name this largest island in the world, an autonomous country within Denmark.",
      "answer": "Greenland or Kalaallit Nunaat"
    },
    {
      "question": "A portion of this modern-day state was organized into the self-governing Cimarron Territory by settlers who moved before the land was surveyed. Inhabitants of what became this state proposed the State of Sequoyah. Several Native American tribes were forced to move to Indian Territory in this state during the Trail of Tears. For ten points, name this state where “Sooners” founded cities like Tulsa.",
      "answer": "Oklahoma"
    },
    {
      "question": "Golden examples of these objects are reflected on a black background in “Aftermath of Obliteration of Eternity,” one of Yayoi Kusama’s Infinity Mirror Rooms. Man Ray depicted five of these objects in a 1930 “Rayograph,” which he created by using these objects and photosensitive paper. Near the center of Picasso’s war protest painting Guernica, one of these objects explodes near the ceiling. For ten points, name these luminescent household objects developed by Thomas Edison.",
      "answer": [
        "lightbulbs",
        "bulbs",
        "lamps"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This group killed thousands of people in the Sinjar Massacre, which targeted Yazidis in the region of Nineveh. On October 27, 2019, the leader of this group committed suicide after being cornered in the Idlib province of Syria; he was replaced by Abu Ibrahim al-Hashimi, whose precise identity is still unconfirmed. Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi led, for ten points, what Wahhabist terrorist group that, at its height in 2015, controlled parts of Syria and Iraq?",
      "answer": [
        "ISIS or ISIL",
        "Islamic State of Iraq and Syria",
        "Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant",
        "Daesh"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This President signed an Agricultural Marketing Act that created a Federal Farm Board, a plan opposed to the controversial-yet-popular McNary-Haugen plan. This man’s administration began a multi-billion dollar intervention program called the Reconstruction Finance Corporation that gave loans to railroads and banks, an active response to the nation’s worst economic performance of the 20th century. For ten points, name this US President who was replaced during the Great Depression by Franklin Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thisobject,whichcontainsadecreefromanassemblyofpriestsinCanopus,wasgiventhedesignation EA24 in the British Museum. Pierre-Francois Bouchard discovered this object at Fort Julien during a Napoleonic campaign. This object, the most visited item in the British Museum, was studied by Jean-Francois Champollion, whose work ushered in modern Egyptology. For ten points, name this slab of rock whose inscribed Greek and Demotic texts helped decipher Egyptian hieroglyphics.",
      "answer": "Rosetta Stone"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1603, an ice floe destroyed this city’s first permanent bridge, which connected it to the jurydyka of Praga. A shoemaker named Jan Kilinski led the armed peasantry of this city against the occupying Russian Empire in a 1794 uprising. Ju¨rgen Stroop suppressed an uprising in this city, eventually sending most of the rebels to Treblinka and other death camps. A 1943 ghetto uprising took place in, for ten points, what capital city of Poland?",
      "answer": "Warsaw"
    },
    {
      "question": "After winning this event in 1987, Harry Carson dumped a bucket of popcorn over President Reagan’s head at the White House. CEO Jed York claimed to have “pulled the plug” on one of these events in 2013, refuting Ray Lewis’ claim that the power outage at the Louisiana Superdome was a conspiracy. For ten points, name this event, annually the most-watched television program in the United States, that determines the champion of the NFL.",
      "answer": [
        "Super Bowl",
        "Super Bowl 21 and/or 47"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After this ruler ignored a plea for peace, John Dickinson drafted a “Declaration of the Causes and Necessity of Taking Up Arms.” This monarch appointed Lord Rockingham as Prime Minister in favor of Lord Grenville. The Olive Branch Petition was rejected by this ruler, who later was forced to accept peace with the United States after Lord Cornwallis’s men surrendered at Yorktown. For ten points, name this British king during the American Revolution.",
      "answer": "George III"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was briefly ruled by the Thirty Tyrants, a client government of their rival. Citizens of this city could vote to expel others by depositing pottery shards in urns, a process known as ostracism that was used against statesmen like Themistocles. During this city’s Golden Age under Pericles, the Parthenon was built. For ten points, name this “birthplace of democracy,” a powerful city-state of ancient Greece.",
        "answer": "Athens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Themistocles persuaded the Athenians to create a “wooden wall” by improving this military force with the construction of dozens of triremes, which were later used at the Battle of Salamis.",
        "answer": "Athenian navy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Washington Cabell from Tennessee led a committee that decided to revise this act instead of preparing for war. The British violation of neutrality during the Chesapeake Affair encouraged Congress to pass this act, which was later expanded in the Non-Intercourse Act. This act was personified as a turtle in a political cartoon biting a man who says “Oh! This cursed Ograbme.” For ten points, name this economically crippling 1807 act that banned all foreign ships from entering US ports.",
        "answer": "Embargo Act of 1807"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of this President’s final acts was revoking the Embargo Act of 1807 after fifteen ineffectual months.",
        "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist was succeeded by Sir Aaron Klug on a project that determined the structure of the polio virus at Birkbeck College. This scientist split research on another project with Maurice Wilkins, and with graduate student Raymond Gosling, this scientist used X-ray diffraction to create her famous Photo 51. For ten points, name this English scientist whose work on determining the structure of DNA was co-opted by Watson and Crick.",
        "answer": "Rosalind Elsie Franklin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Using Gosling and Franklin’s work, both Franklin and the Watson-Crick team determined that the A and B forms of DNA have this structure.",
        "answer": "right-handed double helix"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Near the end of Queen Anne’s War, riots named for this commodity in Boston led to the poor breaking the rudder of a ship owned by merchant Andrew Belcher. To offset the development of rickets in the UK, the government added calcium to this food during World War II. Juvenal likely coined a term for appeasement of the masses by pairing this food with circuses. Marie Antoinette was said to have proclaimed “Let them eat cake!” during a shortage of, for ten points, what staple baked food?",
        "answer": "bread"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Flour War broke out among French peasants during the reign of this king, the husband of Marie Antoinette.",
        "answer": "Louis XVI"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This piece was premiered in a tent outside the unfinished Cathedral of Christ the Saviour. The tambourine and English horn introduce the folk-tune “At the Gate, At My Gate” in this piece, which opens with four cellos and two violas playing the hymn “Oh Lord, Save Thy People.” This piece’s use of “La Marseillaise” is overtaken by “God Save the Tsar,” during which live cannons fire. The Battle of Borodino is commemorated by, for ten points, what Tchaikovsky overture named for the year of Russia’s victory over France?",
        "answer": [
          "1812 Overture",
          "The Year 1812"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Cathedral of Christ the Saviour was built in this Russian city. Stalin ordered the cathedral torn down to build a new Palace of the Soviets, which was scrapped during World War II.",
        "answer": "Moscow"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These people allegedly saluted Mount Kaimon and dropped flowers as they departed. An instruction manual designed for these people commanded them to shout “hissatsu” in their final moments and look for a point of entry between a smoke stack and a bridge. The term “typhoon of steel” was applied to the Battle of Okinawa due to the prevalence of Mitsubishi Zeros piloted by, for ten points, what Japanese pilots who carried out suicide attacks?",
        "answer": [
          "kamikaze pilots",
          "Tokubetsu Kogekitai"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Centuries earlier, the term “kamikaze” was used to describe the typhoons that prevented this grandson of Genghis Khan from invading the Japanese islands.",
        "answer": "Kublai Khan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was allegedly so impressed by ally Isaac Brock that he presented the general to his troops, saying “this is a man!” The numbers of this man’s armies swelled after the New Madrid Earthquake was interpreted as a sign to join him; those alliances disintegrated with his death at the Battle of the Thames. For ten points, name this brother of “the Prophet,” a Shawnee chief who led a coalition of natives in support of England during the War of 1812.",
        "answer": "Tecumseh"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Union general and leader of a “March to the Sea” through Georgia was given the name Tecumseh by his father.",
        "answer": "William Tecumseh Sherman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Non-dualistic philosophy is touted in this faith’s Advaita Vedanta, inspiring movements like the medieval Bhakti Movement. Governor General Hastings defeated an empire of this faith named the Maratha in the third British war against them. With the arrival of spring, members of this faith celebrate its Festival of Color, Holi. For ten points, name this religion, the majority faith of India.",
        "answer": "Hinduism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The minority religions of India include this faith, whose adherents formed an empire in the Punjab in the early 19th century. Nanak, who lived in the early 16th century, was this religion’s founder and first guru.",
        "answer": "Sikhism"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Andrew Carnegie",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Commodity, an alloy of iron and carbon, whose industry he dominated.",
          "answer": "steel industry"
        },
        {
          "question": "Large western Pennsylvania city where his business empire was centered.",
          "answer": "Pittsburgh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of Standard Oil who he passed as “richest American” after selling his company.",
          "answer": "John D. Rockefeller"
        },
        {
          "question": "American financier who bought Carnegie’s company for over $300 million in 1901.",
          "answer": "John Pierpont “J.P.” Morgan Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "1889 essay in which Carnegie argued that industry leaders should gain, then donate, their riches.",
          "answer": "The Gospel of Wealth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Detective agency that his manager hired to put down the Homestead Strike.",
          "answer": "Pinkerton National Detective Agency"
        },
        {
          "question": "Aforementioned manager, who was nearly assassinated by Alexander Berkman.",
          "answer": "Henry Clay Frick"
        },
        {
          "question": "IndustrialistcolleagueandTreasurySecretaryunderthreepresidentswhopartiallynamesaPittsburgh university.",
          "answer": [
            "Andrew Mellon",
            "Carnegie Mellon University"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "France in World War I",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French capital city and namesake of a German siege gun that weighed half a million pounds.",
          "answer": "Paris Gun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Either of the two countries allied in the Triple Entente with France.",
          "answer": [
            "Russia and/or United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French city where the treaty ending World War I was signed.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Versailles"
        },
        {
          "question": "French Prime Minister at the end of the war, known as “The Tiger.”",
          "answer": "Georges Clemenceau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Forest on the northern border of France that the Germans pushed through in August 1914.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Ardennes Forest"
        },
        {
          "question": "September 1914 battle, a “miracle” for the French that turned the German advance into a stalemate.",
          "answer": "First Battle of the Marne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longest battle of the war, fought in 1916 over the Meuse Heights.",
          "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Allied Commander of the French forces who criticized the peace as an “armistice for 20 years” because it was too lenient.",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Foch"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Oil",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Body of water that names a 1991 war triggered by Saddam Hussein’s invasion of oil-rich Kuwait.",
          "answer": "Persian Gulf War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country led by Hussein that began that war.",
          "answer": "Iraq"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only charter member of OPEC from South America, led from Caracas.",
          "answer": "Venezuela"
        },
        {
          "question": "SouthAmericancountrywherethestate-ownedoilcompany,Petrobras,wasfoundtobecontroversially corrupt in Operation Car Wash.",
          "answer": "Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where oil money fueled the development of Dubai.",
          "answer": "United Arab Emirates or UAE"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose Baku oil fields were targeted by Joseph Stalin.",
          "answer": "Azerbaijan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Libyan colonel and dictator who may have hired Carlos “the Jackal” to kidnap OPEC ministers in 1975.",
          "answer": "Muammar al-Gaddafi"
        },
        {
          "question": "South American country where the Stabroek oil field marked its first production in December 2019.",
          "answer": "Guyana"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A Reconciliation Park at the site of the Tulsa Race Riot is named for an African- American historian of this surname. From Slavery to Freedom author John Hope had this surname, as did William, a Loyalist leader during the American Revolution who was the (20 pts)",
        "last colonial governor of New Jersey. A man with this surname was appointed postmaster of the (10 pts)",
        "American colonies in 1753 and founded the Pennsylvania Gazette. For ten points, give this surname of founding father and inventor Benjamin."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Franklin",
        "John Hope Franklin, William Franklin, and/or Benjamin Franklin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In The Open Society and Its Enemies, Karl Popper claimed that this philosopher’s political thought contained all the elements of totalitarianism. In a work written by this philosopher, a man discusses the role of piety in his decision to prosecute his father. In addition to (20 pts)",
        "Euthyphro [youth-ih-fro], this philosopher wrote a work featuring the (10 pts)",
        "Allegory of the Cave. For ten points, name this author of The Republic whose dialogues depict the teachings of his mentor, Socrates."
      ],
      "answer": "Plato or Platon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Bertrand Goldberg designed a pair of skyscrapers in this city that feature 19 floors of spiral parking ramps and a small dock for riverboats, the Marina City apartment complex. This city’s most upscale commercial district, the Magnificent Mile, is found in the (20 pts)",
        "Water Tower District, named for a building that survived an 1871 disaster. This city’s Millennium Park, which opened four years late, contains Anish Kapoor’s (10 pts)",
        "Cloud Gate, a sculpture nicknamed “the Bean.” For ten points, name this Midwestern city whose architecture was heavily redesigned after a “Great” 1871 fire."
      ],
      "answer": "Chicago"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this family exiled the Strozzi and launched a war against Lucca. Opponents of this family included Francesco Salviati, who orchestrated a plot to kill some of its members during high Mass in the (20 pts)",
        "Pazzi conspiracy. The Albizzi attempted to curb the influence of this family by expelling one of their leading members, but that man, (10 pts)",
        "Cosimo, returned the next year. Pope Leo X was a member of this family, as was Lorenzo the Magnificent. Michelangelo was under the patronage of, for ten points, what family that ruled medieval Florence?"
      ],
      "answer": "Medici family"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author, who defended Henry Miller in the essay “Inside the Whale,” described accepting the conditions of his age as “to say you accept concentration camps [...] and political murders.” This author translated an Ecclesiastes passage into “modern language of the worst sort” in a work that proposed six rules to prevent writing bad (20 pts)",
        "English. This author of “Politics and the English Language” recounted his experiences as a police officer in Burma in (10 pts)",
        "“Shooting an Elephant” and in the Spanish Civil War in Homage to Catalonia. For ten points, name this author whose anti-totalitarian fiction includes 1984 and Animal Farm."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George Orwell",
        "Eric Arthur Blair"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An order to destroy this ship may have been rescinded when Thomas Hardy’s wife allegedly broke into tears upon hearing the news. In its early career, this ship served as the flagship for Augustus Keppel at the Ushants. This ship was painted (20 pts)",
        "black and yellow so it could be more easily identified in a battle where it led a fleet into splitting the lines of Pierre Villeneuve. The (10 pts)",
        "expectation that “every man do their duty” was broadcast from this ship, whose commander was killed in action against a Franco-Spanish fleet. For ten points, name this flagship for Horatio Nelson at Trafalgar."
      ],
      "answer": "HMS Victory"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A woman who married into this family had tomatoes thrown at her in Switzerland while on her “Rainbow Tour.” Supporters of a leader from this family were killed in the Ezeiza Massacre. (20 pts)",
        "Jorge Videla led a coup against a leader of the Justicialist party from this family, which was supported by the “shirtless ones,” the (10 pts)",
        "descamisados. After a champion of women’s suffrage died of cancer in 1952, the patriarch of this family re-married Isabel in 1961. For ten points, name this surname shared by Evita and her husband, a 20th century Argentinian president named Juan."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Per´on family",
        "Eva “Evita” Per´on",
        "Juan Per´on",
        "Isabel Per´on"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Denis Kearny threatened to manufacture balloons for dropping dynamite on one of these places. People who came to one of these places after a 1906 earthquake were called “paper sons.” (20 pts)",
        "In one of these places, Doyers Street became known as “Murder Alley” due to violence among Tong gangs. Immigrants settled in one of these places in San Francisco after the repeal of an 1882 (10 pts)",
        "Exclusion Act. Paifang gates and dragon decorations are common in, for ten points, what urban neighborhoods developed by immigrants from a certain Asian country?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chinatowns",
        "Tangrenjie"
      ]
    }
  ]
}